What we do in life echoes in eternity.
Gladiator is a action, drama, adventure film directed by Ridley Scott.
After the death of Emperor Marcus Aurelius, his devious son takes power and demotes
Maximus, one of Rome's most capable generals who Marcus preferred.
Eventually, Maximus is forced to become a gladiator and battle to the death
against other men for the amusement of paying audiences.
Maximus, played by Russell Crowe.
Commodus, played by Joaquin Phoenix.
Lucilla, played by Connie Nielsen.
Proximo, played by Oliver Reed.
Marcus Aurelius, played by Richard Harris.
Gracchus, played by Derek Jacobi.
Gladiator is a 2000 epic action adventure drama film directed by Ridley Scott and written by
David Franzoni, John Logan, and William Nicholson from a story by Franzoni.
It stars Russell Crowe, Joaquin Phoenix, Connie Nielsen, Oliver
Reed, Derek Jacobi, Djimon Hounsou, and Richard Harris.
Crowe portrays Maximus Decimus Meridius, a Roman general who is betrayed when Commodus, the
ambitious son of Emperor Marcus Aurelius, murders his father and seizes the throne.
Reduced to a slave, Maximus becomes a gladiator and rises through the ranks of the
arena, determined to avenge the murders of his family and the emperor.
The screenplay, initially written by Franzoni,
was inspired by the 1958 Daniel P.
Mannix novel Those About to Die.
The script was acquired by DreamWorks Pictures, and
Scott signed on to direct the film.
Principal photography began in January 1999 and wrapped in May of that year.
Production was complicated by the script being rewritten multiple times and
by the death of Oliver Reed before production was finished.
Gladiator had its world premiere in Los Angeles, California, on May 1, 2000.
The film was released in the United States on May 5, 2000, by DreamWorks
and internationally on May 12, 2000, by Universal Pictures.
The film grossed $466 million worldwide, becoming the second-highest-grossing film of 2000,
and won five Academy Awards, including Best Picture and Best Actor for Crowe.
A sequel, Gladiator II, was released in 2024.
The film explores themes of gladiator, rome, italy, arena, senate, roman empire.
The tone is emotional.